we have today Mike Lewis he's a research scientist at Facebook AI Research
working on natural language processing so previously he was a postdoc at the
University of Washington and working with Luke Zettlemoyer
and on the search based structure prediction
he completed his phd at the University of Edinburgh
and based on combining distributional and logical approaches
to semantics he has a mastery degree from the University of Oxford and won
the best paper award on EMNLP in 2016.
so uh without further ado let's get started with today's presentation
okay well thank you very much for the introduction Alfredo and inviting me
to talk um so yeah this lecture just wants to
try giving a high level overview of how deep learning
is used for natural languages processing these days
so i think it's [inaudible] it's been really dramatic progress in nlp in the last few
years with the playing deep learning um so
these days i mean you can get machine translation systems which will produce
translations which blind human narrators prefer the ones
produced by professional translators um you can make some question answering
systems that you ask them a question give me wikipedia
and they'll give you answers that are [inaudible] more accurate than the ones that
people will give you i could like have language models that
can like generate uh several paragraphs of fluent text
and for all of these things if you'd asked me like maybe five years ago i'd
have told you there's absolutely no way any of this is
possible in 2020 but um there seems to be a few
techniques that have been introduced that have really
made dramatic differences and one really nice properties actually
you can achieve all of these things with fairly generic models so
all the models for all these tasks actually look very similar
uh there's just a few high-level principles which are really useful
um so i'm gonna be covering quite a lot ground on this quite quickly
so please interrupt me often with questions
um right so yeah um also one thing i should say is
that with all the progress we've been seeing
in nlp uh probably a lot of stuff i'm going to tell you right now is going to
be out to date in a year or two i mean i hope
we continue to make progress and stuff continues to
be out today so as well as like explaining some of the models we're
using i want to try and sort of give you some intuitions about what kinds of
principles are working out well which will hopefully have a bit more of
a shelf life okay so um the first
topic i want to cover this lecture is language modeling
language modeling isn't necessarily a useful task in itself but it seems to be
a really good building block for introducing all the
techniques that we'll need later on um so uh i don't know any of you seen
this before this is an example from a language model called gpt-2
which came out in 2019. um so what's going on here is that we've
got some humans played some uh introduction
here about um scientists finally heard of unicorns of
the andes that apparently speak english and then given that text they've asked
this language model to write some more texts and stats of that
and the text we get here is actually quite
impressive like everyone was really shocked that language models could work
this well uh last year so you can see um
the convenient text seems actually quite plausible for a news article about this
it's um talk to me talk about unicorns um
the text is very fluent grammatical it's not really any flaws there and
it seems to like invent quite a lot of details like the name of the scientists
who discovered them um obviously all this is complete
nonsense nothing here is true but um also
none of this will look like anything the model was ever trained on like i'm
pretty sure this paragraph over his unicorn has like
no neighbors anywhere on the internet this
is all completely new language but it's all
actually quite high quality text um i'm not going to read all this out
but like if you read the rest of the article that wrote then
um there are some flaws but they're quite hard to spot and generally
uh this seems to be quite a good language model
so i'm gonna try and show you like the kind of techniques you need to actually
build the lines model that works as well all right so um
[Silence] very briefly what is language model so
language model is just a basic density estimation for text
so we're going to assign a probability to
uh every possible string and hopefully when puts more probability on like
strings which are fluent english than other strings
um so how do we model this density well um obviously
there are quite a lot of possible sentences
exponentially many so we can't just predict classified suits directly
um there are different techniques you can do for this but the one i'm going to
talk about is the one that's most popularly used which is
basically to factorize this distribution using the chain rule
um so here all we're going to do is um just [inaudible] to say it's going
to predict the first word then predict the second word given the first then
the third given the previous two um this is an exact characterization it
doesn't cost us anything to do like this um so really what we turned is
the density estimation problem into a series of classification problems
these classification problems are the form given a bunch of texts predict the
next word and that's going to be a theme through a
lot of techniques we have in this talk so more concretely we have this uh from
this example i showed you before we got this
um string the model output so like the scientists
name the population after the distinct detail on orbits and you've got to
predict the next word and uh the correct word in this case is
unicorn okay so um
at high level all these language models look something like this basically we
input this text into a neural network somehow
the neural network will map all this context onto a vector
this vector represents the next word and then we're going to
have some big word about matrix so our um word embedding matrix will
basically contain a vector for every possible word model knows how to output
and then all we need to do is compute the similarity by just doing a dot
product between the context vector and each of these
word vectors and uh we'll get a likelihood of
predicting the next word then we'll just train this model by
maximum likelihood in the obvious way okay so um
i mean the detail here is often we don't deal with words directly we deal with
things called subwords or even characters but um all
the modeling techniques remain the same all right so um
how all skills here is in this context encoder
how do we build this um so kind of the first approach people
took for this is um basically convolutional models
so these convolution models kind of encode this
uh inductive bias that language can has this translation of variance
property we should interpret a phrase the same
way no matter what position it occurs in um so a typical model might look this
way basically first of all for every word we'll just map it to some
vector um which is just a lookup table into an
embedding matrix so the word will get the same vector no
matter what context it appears in and then we'll apply a bunch of layers
of the 1d convolutions followed by non-linearities
until eventually we end up with some kind of vector
representing that context which really really [inaudible] the vector means what should
the next word be um and these models were first
i think this is actually maybe the first language model from bengio in 2003 world's
first neural language model um and uh these kind of convolutional
approaches were actually shared if to work quite well by Yann LeCun
in 2016 if you applied in a modern deep learning
techniques um kind of the these models very fast
which is great um actually speed is very impossible
language modeling because typically we use huge amounts of
training data um there's one come downside which is
that they're only able to really condition on the certain reception field
um so in this kind of toy example uh this word unicorn could only condition
uh the previous uh five words uh because of the sort of kernel width
the number of layers we're using here um obviously like realistic
convolutional models i have a much bigger receptor field like this but
um natural language tends to have extremely long range dependencies i mean
uh for an extreme example you can imagine if you're like trying to build a
language model of a complete book it might actually help you to be able to
condition on the title of the book at all time steps and
obviously the title will be hundreds of thousands of words
previously and it's quite hard to kind of build this into
build a convolutional receptor field big enough to do this
okay so how do we condition our model context
i guess um the most popular approach until a couple years ago
was uh what's called the current neural networks
um this is kind of a conceptually quite straightforward idea that basically at
every time set we're going to maintain some state so have some state coming in
from the previous time step which represents
what we've read so far we'll combine the state with uh
the recurrent word we've read and we'll use that to update our states
and then we'll just iterate this for as many time steps
as we need um so i think this seems like quite a
natural model of reading i mean i think for the most part people kind of
read left or right and maintain some kind of states
as they go at least in principle as well you can model unbounded contexts like
this um at least in principle like the
say the title of a book would affect the hidden states
of the last word of the book um in practice so there are some fairly
significant issues with this model firstly um there's kind of
no free lunch here so by the time the effect of trying to maintain
mistakes is we're going to compress the whole
history of the document reading into a single vector at each time step
and then you can't once you've read a word you can never look at it again you
have to memorize that and that means you have to
actually have to cram a huge amount of information into a
single vector and this is firstly it's a kind of a
bottleneck involved also i mean there's a question about how much
information you can really store in one vector but
also um it's kind of a practical learning problem to you
that's the the um you get an issue called the vanishing gradient problem
where it means that you know every time you go
through one of these steps then you you'll have some kind of
non-linearity which will mean that the effective words in the past
will kind of get exponentially smaller each time step
that means that once you have uh no gradient for a particular word in the
past it's very hard to actually suddenly learn later on
that word was impossible. um one final issue i want to mention
with [inaudible] is they're actually quite slow
um the reason for this is particularly for training
um so the reason is that in order to like um
build your state for a particular work you actually have to
build your state for every previous word first
let me essentially have a big for loop that's going over your entire document
and the longer your document is the bigger this for loop is
and [inaudible] most of these operations you can't actually compute in
parallel you actually have to do it sequentially and one gpu
hardware is really based around being able to do
operations in parallel um okay
so the convolutional network didn't have this problem it's everything's in
parallel but on the other hand you get this boundary
receptor field and the recurrent models you have
in principle an infinite amount of receptor field
but it's quite slow to train so the solution to this is now what's
called the transformer um which is the model that's used in all
state-of-the-art nlp systems these days um so i'm going to go through
transformer in quite a lot more detail when i did
the rnns or cnns um transformers were introduced in 2017
by Ashish Vaswani and famous paper called attention is all
you need and they really revolutionize lots of
NLP so i included a figure here from the
original transformer paper um i don't know how confusing is this to you
certainly when i first saw this figure in 2017
it took me quite a while to get my head around it and there's
quite a lot of details going on in these boxes so i'm going to
just try to slowly drill into them all right so what's going on um
basically you see we have this input state this um
end times this transformer block and then um an output phase
so this end times block thing just means we're going to unroll
uh the same block with different parameters
a certain number of times there so the example has uh
six layers which i think had the original transform paper which seems
quite cute these days um these days people are training models
with billions of parameters and uh many many dozens of layers
all right so i'm just going to drill into this box
more detail so this can be the core of the transformer the transformer block
you see it's actually incorporated to two different sub layers
[Notification Sound] um which are both very important um
sub layer 2 is maybe the more obvious one this is just a big
feedforward network um it could be any mlp but it's
important it's actually quite expressive um
and beneath we have this multi-headed attention module
the multi-head attention is kind of the key building block behind transformers
and why they work um so
this sublayer is also connected by these um boxes labeled add and norm
so the add part means this is a residual connection
um which helps stopping the gradients vanishing in large models
uh the norm here means uh layer normalization
i'm not going to the layer norm in detail here but
it's actually very important to make these models work and there's actually
some subtleties about how exactly you do the layer normalization that
makes a big difference in practice uh hey excuse me i have a question sure
uh so this isn't immediately clear but
could you talk a little bit more about just the intuition behind using
multi-headed attention as opposed to a single head
i mean presumably each head learns something different
and attends over its input differently but
what's what was sort of the intuition behind that
um i'll ask that question a bit i'm going to go through
uh exactly what multi-headed attention is a bit first and then i'll try and get some
iterations as to why this is a good thing to do
uh if we don't answer your question then please
follow me up in a few slides time thank you
any other questions at this stage by the way
uh i have a question uh used that the the transformer module uses layer
normalization uh why can you provide some intuition into why that works
better than group normalization or uh old-fashioned normalization
um i don't think i can actually give a very
satisfying technical answer to this and i think a lot of this is quite empirical
as to why in nlp we layer norm works great and
in computer vision batch norm works great um a nice prosperous layer norm
is that it doesn't depend on the batch dimension uh which
batch norm does so uh in practice that's quite a big
advantage because it's quite hard to train with large
batches with them very large models yeah you can see people written lots of
papers and actually why things like that even work for computer version i think
at least that's how i read it's there's still some debate as to actually what
it's doing um maybe the intuition is the original
paper why even batch norms are not great
um so personally i would say this is one of the slightly unsatisfying
things in deep learning where it works but it's a little bit unclear
why okay thank you yeah maybe i was waiting
with a more satisfying answer than that [Drinking]
another question is coming here is do transformers share weights across
time steps like rnn lstms uh yeah great question i should have
made that clear um yeah so all these weights can be shared across
timesteps um so it's kind of convolutional nonsense
um so you have one block and you'll play it
every time step uh you can actually also apply them use
the same weights and every layer and that works quite well too
but it's not what people normally do thank you
any other questions so far i think those were the questions i read
so far on the chat okay so uh what is this mysterious
multi-headed attention thing um so here's another figure i don't know
if this helps um uh so basically you can
compute these three quantities called um b k and q here they stand for a query
key and value respectively um
do the scale dot product attention operation and then concatenate the
outputs all right so drilling into this scale
dot product attention um eventually we will run out of boxes to
expand um it looks something like this um
so we're going to do compute this query and key
do a dot products and softmax and use this
as a way to some of the values i don't worry that it makes sense i will
do more detail so let's look at this example um
where the context here is let's say these horned silver-whites
and we're trying to create the next word which in the example before was uh
unicorn so um
for the word we're trying to predict we're going to like compute this value
called the query and for all the previous words we're
going to compute the quantity called the key and
these are linear layers based on the current states of this layer
um tomorrow we're going to be coding this in in practice so we're going to be
seeing this in like only the small details in the in
the code as well okay so
um you can think of this query as the model asking a question over here it's
context so far but it's going to help you predict what the next word should be
so the query could be something like um tell me what previous adjective is or
tell me what the uh previous determiner is
um and a disabler's word like these here
and then for the keys they're going to be things that sort of
label the current word with telling you some information about it so they could
be saying this word is an adjective this word is a
determiner this word is a verb something like that
or can be something more complex like it could be like a
any [inaudible] relation like co-reference or something
so [inaudible] completely as a questions query and then it's going to
compute just do a dot product with all of the
keys and use this to compute and then you do softmax as well and this
is going to induce a distribution over all the
previous words so here you can imagine a query
something like telling me what previous adjective is and the
attention will produce this kind of distribution over
these three previous words it's going to put most probability mass on either horn
or silver white um
we're also going to compute this other value this is the quantity called the
value and we'll do that for all the previous
words as well and maybe the value will tell you
something slightly more about what the contents of the word is
and then i'm going to compute this hidden state by basically marginalizing
out the attention distribution so here this
hidden state is going to be a weighted sum of the values
of all the previous words that's going to be
weight by the probability of that word um so
that's basically what's going on the left side of this figure here
i left out this detail about the scaling escape that's just a
hack to make the gradients more stable okay um but there's another detail here
which is that uh that's kind of single-headed
attention i've described so far but we're actually gonna do this thing
called multi-headed attention and that basically just means we're gonna
compute the same thing with different queries keys and values
multiple times in parallel so this question before about like what
the intuition behind that is um and really it's like you actually
want let's create the next word you need to
know a lot of different things so just this example before
um uh let's see so let's say the next word
here should be unicorns plural um to know it should be unicorns i mean
you probably want to know both that it's horned and silver white because
uh the conjunction of those makes it more likely to be unicorn
but you also want to know that the uh the determinant here was these
not a if it was like a horn silver white it'd be
unicorn singular the fact is these means it should be unicorn plural so you can
plural it [inaudible] so you actually need to like look at all
these three words at once to have a good idea
what the next word should be a multi-attention is a way of like letting
each word look at multiple previous words simultaneously
a question here is why are we actually uh in need of using the softmax
why do we use this yeah it's a good question um
i think firstly i mean [inaudible] on normalization
effect is probably good i mean otherwise when you got longer
sequences this uh summation would get kind of bigger and
bigger the further you went through so having a normalization
is probably good the normalization also kind of lets the model um
discard information to you so it can say this word
just isn't relevant um which is good i think i have seen people
experiment with using things like ReLu instead
so which kind of different different way of discarding information but
i think the evidence is softmaxes work the best
uh another question sorry i may have missed this um
the mask there in pink don't know what that is briefly right mask is actually
important um so
i'm going to say make a point first um so one of the really big wins about this
whole [inaudible] multi-headed attention is
that it's extremely paralyzable um so now this
computation of queries keys and values a given time step depends on
what you're doing at any of the other time steps so
unlike your current network you can actually compute all of these
simultaneously um which plays very well with um the
kind of hardware we have these days so not only are we going to put all the
different heads at once we're going to compute all the time steps at once in a
single forward pass um
so that's great except that if you're computing all the time steps
at once there's nothing to actually stop you
um words looking at the future since like
auto-regressive factorization we're dealing with here then
we only want words conditioned on previous words
um but as i've spread them all so far the words could look at future words too
which is the problem because then they can cheat
and use themselves on future context to predict themselves
so the solutions that here is um uh so it's what we call self-attention
masking so a mask is just a upper triangular matrix that sort of uh
has zeros and lower triangle and like negative infinity in the upper triangle
and we're going to just add this to the attention scores
and the effect of that is going to be that um every word to the left has a
much higher attention score than everywhere to the right so the model
will only end up practicing using words to the left but this is deterministic
mask without trainable weights um just values either zero or negative
or infinity uh so you'd only mask in case of an
application-specific training task correct if you had to just
build representations for example you wouldn't need to mask because it wouldn't
matter uh yeah that's a great question and so
we'll go to more general representation learning later so
uh most of the time you just want a text encoder you don't need to mask them
bidirectional context is absolutely helpful um
in this case language modeling which we're working through so far then
the mask is sort of crucial to make them all mathematically correct and compute
the correct factorization but yeah great
question thanks okay um
okay so uh one other detail we need to do to make all this work
is add something should be input over positional writing
so as i describe small so far it's actually
um it's doing a low bias model it knows very little about language the inputs
could be anything and it would work so um
in particular it's like i mean you can model a set or a graph or anything like
this it should be fine um but we know
i mean in language there are some properties which are useful like for
example um there's an ordering to words which is
really important to how you interpret them
and this one doesn't actually know anything about that and that's in
contrast to the convolutional models and the parallel models i showed you earlier
which both have different ways of encoding the
order of text um so one of the techniques that was
introduced in this paper was called positional embedding um the
different ways you can do this they describe something in the paper
which is slightly weird actually i'm not going to describe
but it works just as well to essentially learn separate embedding for every time
step so for every positioning document zero one two three four five
you just learn separate embedding and then you add this to your input
so your input now is a summation of the word vector and some kind of positional
vector and it's very simple but it gives the
model kind of the order information it needs and it
works great okay so why are these models so good why
does everyone use them um i think the really powerful thing about
the model is that it kind of gives you direct connections
between every pair of words so each word can directly access the
hidden state of every previous word um and
that's a contrast to convolutional model could barely get the state of all the
words in this receptor field but nothing further back in time than that
and our current model um the state had to go through his
bottleneck of each time at each time step so
um you can actually directly access the previous words
beyond the like literally one previous word anything further than the past
had to get somehow compressed and you have lost information about this
for self attention you can in principle put 100% attention on
any word in the distant past and see exactly what was there
and this just makes it a really powerful model it like avoids things like uh
issues like vanishing gradients quite effectively
um and amazingly can just learn very expressive functions very easily
the other great thing about this is how paralyzable it is i mean
so the one hand this model's doing quite a lot of computation in that it's doing
uh this um so the self-attention operation is quadratic
basically because every word can look at every other word
and that sounds quite slow but the really nice thing is you can do it in
parallel so because all these operations are
independent to each other you just do it as one big matrix multiplication so
even though sometimes you probably do kind of more
add multiply operations and you would do with the equivalent RNN
you can do all these operations um much faster because you do them all at once
rather sequentially so this is a really good trade-off
um i also want to quickly talk about some other things that's great
the stuff like um multi-headed attention and positional embeddings and stuff so
i've got all the attention when transformers were first released
but transformers also came along with a whole bag of
other tricks as well and these tricks were all
actually really important to make this stuff work
um and sometimes this paper really kind of modernized NLP i think
um so for example i've mentioned about this useful layer normalization before
[inaudible] it's really helpful um they also have doing these things
like um these learning rate schedules so uh for
whatever reason to make transformers work well
uh you have to sort of linearly warm up your learning rate from
some from zero to your goal learning rate over
several thousand steps um and people do do warm learning rates
warm-up learning rates in other settings but transformers really really need this
to work um also the things that the
initialization actually really do matter with these and
some initializations don't work um and they're throwing these other
tricks like a label smoothing at the output which
uh again wasn't invented in this paper but it turns out
quite helpful for the task like machine translation
all right um so to give you some idea how well these things
are working these models described so far um
here are some results on a language modeling depth benchmark um
so the number on the right is what's called perplexity which is a
measure of the likelihood of held out data and here lower is better
um so let's see you see that an lcm for 2016 gets perplexity of
uh 48 um you see that Yann Dauphin's convolutional
models uh from 2016 uh doing quite a bit better at
about 20 about 37. uh also people played around with a
whole bunch of RNN variants like you speak dozens of
papers on how you make variations in LSTMs and some of these
getting low 30s as well but then when you introduce transformers
you get a really big jump down to go to 18 and 20.
and in terms of language modeling that's a really enormous geometry performance
um i should say these gains we saw were particularly
large on uh kind of long context language modeling so language modeling
where so there's some benchmarks where you
just get a single sentence to predict uh on this task you actually get a whole
wikipedia article so uh potentially thousands of words and
the transformers really shine on this what
you've got thousands of words context model and you need to
retain information across all of them okay um
uh yeah so there's a quick comparison just to visualize how transformers and LSTMs
look which it's going to indicate some points
of shame before so in the LSTM you have a lot fewer connections between
the words like everything's kind of very sequential left to right
and transform but you don't have any of this um
so every word is directly connected to every other word
um i guess you should say as well in some senses maybe slightly unnatural
well for reading so it kind of suggests that however as well as reading text and
every time it reads a word it goes and really reads
every other word very quickly um but it's very effective
okay one other good thing about transformers is they do scale up
extremely well so um with tasks like language modeling
you get essentially infinite amounts of data because
it's just hundreds of billions of words out there it's far more than you'd ever
need uh that means to actually fit this kind
of distribution you need very big models and you just keep on
adding transform parameters transformers they keep on
just working better and better uh the examples i showed you forward
from this gpt-2 model with two billion parameters which was
uh quite big for 2019 but apparently 2020 or up to
17 billion and there are rumors 100 billion parameter models will be coming
along soon uh excuse me i have a question
aha you said transform is a really good for scaling up
i was just wondering in a language modeling task if we have like
say a ten thousand twenty thousand word document in an
RNN we can just insert a word step by step and we
wouldn't need uh a lot of memory per se like
for for a transformer we need to have a batch size of 10000
wouldn't we like uh like the the length of the sequence but if we have a
really long sequence can we model these long term
dependencies yeah that's a really great question um i
actually meant to mention this point so um
two things they want to say so firstly you're absolutely right the
self-attention is because of quadratic the expense obviously grows super
linearly and that is a problem in practice it means
um so mostly transformers do 512 token context
windows which is fairly affordable for gpus
i love these language models to do more than that let me about a few thousand
tokens um which is kind of limits what we can
do um but it's definitely the case that a
vanilla transformer can't model say a 50000 word book at all
um there it's like this whole cutting-edge industry recently building
various transformers which can do long sequences um it's very hot
topic right now um there's most things you can do but
one kind of thing you do is like if you replace
self-attention with something like nearest neighbor search
uh you can do the self-attention uh subquadratic time and that makes it
faster um
there are also versions that try to do kind of sparse attention where like you
can't attend to every previous word directly but
you kind of have some dilated uh set of previous words you can look at
and you don't get quite a direct connection to every word but you can
sort of guarantee that you have short paths across every word
um there are also things like compressed transformers we try to um
[inaudible] and to sort of uh compress the pre little distant passes
into shorter representations um
okay so you brought up the question of RNN so at impress time absolutely a RNN
can model infinite context where there absolutely
no additional cost which is great i mean they can put
like a million words and output really first just fine
um the regression actually is using this context and um
that's probably it's not so at training time
um you can't do this at training time you actually have to back propagate
through what's what's called back propogate
through time where the LSTM would um
have to give model one context like gradient will have to propagate all the
way back through the sort of all the recurrent steps to make
a difference to the distant pass there uh in practice firstly the gradient will
vanish like well before you hit a thousand steps and
also this is very expensive so this is at
training time system for free and this back propagation operation will
get more and more expensive the longer sequences
you're modeling so that means you can't actually really learn to
uh well this is the pass even interesting it's not expensive you just
wouldn't know what to do with this any practices
you probably just forget it anyway because the
uh you can't remember that much data once
um all right one more quick point in that um
this is interesting uh i guess one case where they'll
where the RNNs do have an advantage is on certain algorithmic tests
um so if you aren't modeling language let's say you're i'm doing something
like addition or trying to like model a parity
of a string um
so you use string of like zeros and ones and ask you either an even number
of ones or not um in those cases
um you basically do actually want to apply literally the same operation every
time step and you can you don't actually have to
have much memory because i mean your state really just needs to be a
zero or one in this case the uh the RNNs actually do
work very well because you can train them on short sequences and they'll
show like great generalizations for long
sequences all these kinds of toy problems
and actually on tray but i imagine the transformer would actually find it much
harder to get that kind of generalization
uh that only really applies to these kind of algorithmic problems in terms of
modeling natural language then uh yeah it seems like various transformers
are going to be much more effective than recurrent nets
thank you that was really helpful um any other questions on transformers?
i've been addressing the questions i could uh via text
so i think it's we are all good right now
okay all right so um next thing we want to cover is uh
what's called decoding or inference for language models so
uh we train this language model this language model puts a
hopefully probability maths on things which good english and
uh their probability on grammatical and nonsensical things um
but if you want to like create these samples like i showed you before and how
do we actually generate stacks
um so often we think about for inference with the graphical model what we care
what we'd like to do is find the max so by creating sentences which
maximizes large world's probability um
unfortunately there's um as i mentioned before there's quite a lot of english
sentences that are possible and we can't just like
score them all to kind of max um also these models don't really
uh there's no dynamic programming here so
sometimes you can't find the max of overexponential structures when you
have a model that factorizes somewhere that lets you build a dynamic program
which lets you kind of share state across different hypotheses um
but these models don't be composed in a friendly way so
kind of whatever choice make the first word could affect all the other
other decisions all right so must given that
uh one thing to do is do greedy decoding um this is where we're just
gonna take the most likely the first word and then given
that word pretty much like second word uh guess was like a third word
um that's okay but it's um there's no guarantee that's
actually gonna meet the most likely sequence you want to output because if
you have happen to make a bad step at some point then you've got
no way of backtracking your search to undo any previous decisions
um this ledger says that exhaustive search is impossible
um and kind of hits middle ground of what's called beam search
um so beam searched is a way of trying to keep track of
an n-best list of hypotheses and then we're going to
uh just every time step try and keep track update this list
with uh you as we've added uh this may be easy to show you an
example um this slides from Abigail See at Stanford um
so uh we start we output let's say
we have the size of two well i'll put these two possible words these are
these are two most likely words now for each of these words we're going
to generate um work out what our [inaudible] like the next
words that so obviously with I or he that does affect
what the next word should be and we'll come with different hypotheses
for each of these um
and then every time we're going to kind of compress these down to
a list of uh two that we're going to continue [inaudible]
so we're looking for the lowest total sum is it correct
uh yeah so these are log likelihoods so
um we actually want the highest sum if that makes sense which should be
where zero would be a probability one oh yeah
so every score is going to be less than zero but we're going to find the
secrets with the whether some of the scores is
the highest did I make sense it is so sorry yeah
i got the the sign flipped i was many like in
magnitude we tried to get the smallest number in magnitude uh
as well as the magnitude yeah sure sorry sorry maybe this is not the most best
way to show this okay how deep does the um does this like tree
go into the beam search when do you stop looking for um like
candidate sequences i guess um all right so we basically
one detail i haven't told you is we have this like end of sentence token
and the end of sentence token means once you once you output that then you
this hypothesis is finished um and the aim is to find complete
hypotheses so from from a start to the end token
that have the highest possible score um so
um we'll just keep on generating you hypotheses
until uh there's no possible new words for
that that would be the k complete hypothesis we have still
okay cool there's another question here why do you think in NMT very very large
beam size will most often result in empty
translations ooh uh great question um i have opinions
on this um so
um the research is good and since it's
guaranteed to give you a higher scoring hypothesis than
the uh greedy search i mentioned in the previous slide
but it's kind of a catch here which is that we're not actually
um at training time we're typically not using a beam
so um at training time we normally just use
kind of the auto regressive factorization i showed you before
where like given the sort of n previous correct
outputs predict the n plus first word um what we're not doing is
exposing the model to its own mistakes in it so when you do beam search
um you can get all kinds of nonsense showing up in your beam for whatever
reason because if you have a very big beam then
probably some of it will be garbage and in these garbage states the model has no
idea what to do because there's never training the situation
um so it's kind of reasonable to expect your model to generalize words like
making great predictions for some completely nonsensical series
of words which is like a very part of its training distribution and
in this case the model can do all kinds of weird and uncerebral
things like maybe they put a very high probability on something else
um very kind of a classic example this i
don't know if this i don't have one here but
you may have seen this language models get stuck in these feedback loops where they
end up just like repeating the same word or phrase infinitely many times i
think it's kind of example this where once the mods like start going into this
kind of loop then it doesn't really know what to do and
the easiest thing for it to carry on doing is
just keep on looping um so yeah i think
the issue [inaudible] beam search is one of uh
not exposing the model to its own mistakes at training time
so it just it put actually puts a bunch of probability amounts and all kinds of
things it shouldn't do um kind of the obvious solution to that
is like why don't you have a beam at training time um
[Distant Noises] there's uh and the short answer that is
because it's expensive uh if you guys go around this whole
inference procedure a training time that firstly gets rid of
all the nice parallelism but we have the transformer and introduces all
the search and also gives you many more things to
score for every training example
so in practice people tend to just ignore this problem and train
create a big model for as long as they can like exposing like nice fast
parallels and you get from this autoregressive version and then at test
time people will often tune the size of their beam to get the
best performance so uh i think that translation like
increasing the beam normally helps up to a point then makes
basically worse again we started covering
uh these weird degene-degenerate outputs
um but yeah that's just the unsatisfying thing people
have to do sorry that's quite a long answer that answer your question
i think uh i think this student i will see now what the student says
like uh that was a question from a student
and there is another question a small one on this current slide
why the why is the a and one in green on the right um
um i could admit i don't know i stole this slide from abby um
i'm not quite sure what point she was trying to make there okay
it's okay oh okay the point actually someone
answer because they are interchangeable regardless of the the the the one you
pick you get both outputs pie and tart
like either or you go for either you go for a or one both of them will
tell you pie tart or pie tart uh i'm not sure um i mean
even if you were to do that then you you can't compress these it's not that you
could get a dynamic program where you can sort of collapse these hypotheses
because the hidden states both these those two hypotheses would still be
different um depending on which path you took
together uh so i don't know but hopefully this
illustrates might beam search is okay okay
okay any more questions on this um
okay this is a bit more description of how the algorithm looks um
basically all you do is every time step you generate
a distribution of next words through thr hypotheses you have
and then you take the top-k hypothesis next words across all your hypotheses
and pull these before you go to the next word
all right so um all right so beam search sometimes is the
right thing to do but um often it actually isn't
uh so this is the result of applying beam search
to the example i showed you before so this example from gpt-2 about like
scientists finding unicorns in the andes um
you can see here that the model is actually
it starts outputting some good stuff and gets stuck in this weird feedback
loop um
so i think yes we're just gonna repeat the same phrase over and
over and over again i'll probably just keep on repeating this phrase
forever i mean i guess kind of what's going on here like once you said this
phrase twice maybe it's just saying the third
time is actually the most likely thing to do and
then all these other hypotheses get very high prob
transitions get right have probability even if they're not good
but there's also kind of a slightly different problem which is like maybe
in some cases we don't actually want the most likely sequence after all um
maybe what we want is something interesting so
you see this problem also a lot in like things like dialogue response generation
so you're trying to build a model to hold
conversation with someone and if you do this kind of beam search often what
you'll get is it will just give you the most generic response to
anything you say so whatever you say it'll be like oh
that's interesting thanks and maybe that actually genuinely
is the most likely thing to do because these responses are good
in most situations um however that's not
actually a very good experience or a very good
system so how about if instead of taking the um
max we're going to sample from the model distribution instead
um so this is a conceptually kind of appealing but it
doesn't actually give you very good output so
uh this is again the result sampling on that same input
um i mean so this is kind of good but then
it goes kind of uh it gets more weird and degenerate as
it goes on um
and again you get to now problem where like once you sample the bad choice
then the models in state was never in training
um and then once it's not stages in during training it's more likely to give
you support bad output and you'll get stuck in these
horrible feedback loops okay um
all right so here's something that actually does work because it was used
to get you those uh beautiful outputs we had before
um unfortunately it's not very satisfying technique but
it's a disclosure um so it's called top-k sampling it's
used introduced by uh Angela Fan a couple years ago
um basically top-k sampling what we're going to do
is truncate our distribution to just taking the k best
and then sample from that um so this advantage of giving us kind
of diversity like choosing randomly amongst like good options but tries to
stop us kind of uh falling off this kind of manifold and
actually good language but when we sample something bad um so the
[inaudible] basis is just chop off the long tail and just sample from the head of the
distribution and this is the sampling for the beam search
is it uh sorry this isn't beam search this is just um generation so
we're gonna um there's not gonna be beam here this
could be one hypothesis i guess you could it creates beam search
too but uh this is actually pure sampling so
i can generate a word in this method then use that to generate the next word
okay um so when you uh do all that then this is finally the
technique that was used during this nice sample
obviously this top-k i'm playing it's a bit of a hack it's not very satisfying
um i was um an author on that paper so i can mean about the method
but um it does seem to work quite well um i guess one thing to be aware of like
when you see these great samples and things like this which
like openly i am very happy to put in their publicity
uh it's kind of useful to know how it's actually made
and this is like this is not like a real sample from all distribution the model
is like not putting uh and it must use probability mass on
this this is generated by uh
doing this slightly weird inference procedure with the model
um i just want to quickly cover like all right so give us some text like this
how do we know if it's any good or not like how do you evaluate this
um so like it's not like evaluating language model it's quite
easy i mean it's language modeling it's task density estimation so you just
look at the log likelihood of that data
um if you want to do instead like uh take some text to model and say if
it's any good or not then uh this is not trivial and
uh it's kind of people tend to use like these automated metrics like BLEU and
ROUGE which measure like and grammar overlap with the reference
but um they're not very satisfying
and this is recent research and trying to do awesome asymmetrics
okay i should place me down for this um all right so this is um that's
unconditional language models um so they're generating samples of text
uh this actually isn't a very useful thing to do what's much more useful is
uh conditional language models so models which will give us a text
given some input generate use some output so
for example you can think about things like um
given a french sentence like translate it into english i've given a document
generate a summary given a dialogue generate the
next response or you can give it a question i'll put the answer
so this is called sequence sequence models
um because you get given some input sequence and then you have to
generate some output sequence um because the first models these are
introduced by Ilya Sutskever um look kind of like this with recurrent
neural networks where basically you'd have some encoded network which
would read your inputs produce some vector which you
modestly called a thought vector and then you'd use this
to initialize your decoder which would generate tokens word
by word again hopefully you get your theme here
like carrying these kind of bottlenecks and recurrence is not a good thing to do
uh you want to have expressive models which you might see everything
uh so there's a variation transformer for sequence sequence models
um here we're going to have a two stacks an encoder stack and decoder stack
uh basically the encoder stack is the same as what i showed you before
apart from the self attention isn't masked so every token the input can look at
every other token in the input the decoder stack will be similar except
that as well as doing the self attention over itself
it's also going to do attention over um the
complete inputs so this means that every token in output
has direct connection to every previous token in the output
um and also to every word in the inputs which makes these models very expressive
and powerful translation scores over
the previous recurrent convolutional models
so what we're training these models typically what we do is we rely on labeled
text so we uh it's a string translation system for
example you try and get lots of manually translated
text it turns out one of the best ways to get this is things like parliament
proceedings because they always translate
the european parliament or write proceedings lots of different languages
um and then you just use those as inputs and now however like
not all languages are represented in the european
parliament um so and these transformers are very data
hungry and like more texts can throw at them the best they will do
um so this question like how we use monolingual text to improve these so
this is actually saying it can we learn without just having
input output pairs uh the way we could do this is a
technique called back translation which is
quite simple conceptually that's our goal is to train a translation system
that inputs german and we'll output english
um first of all we're going to actually do the opposite we're going to train a
reverse translation model which will give an english output german
then we can then run this model over all the english texts we can find and we
can uh find a lot of english text on the
internet and we'll translate it all in german
um and that gives us like lots more pairs of
english and german text and then we're going to train a forward model or try
and translate this german into english um the next thing to see here is
that it doesn't actually matter how good the
initial model is right it doesn't matter if the your reverse model is making
mistakes um so if your reverse model makes
mistakes then your final train data will contain kind of
noisy german translates to clean english um
which might even help regularize your model but probably
shouldn't pass its performance when you show it
a clean german data what's a bitext oh i'm sorry um a bitex just means a
parallel text so the same sentences
in two different languages okay thanks
okay um and the nice thing about back translation is that
the outputs you get are actually always uh you know
high quality because these are the outputs of the system
i think to you uh sentences you found in the wild on
the internet you're just going to create some noisy
inputs that you can use for these pair of these outputs
um could you go back a slide the third point translate billions of
words of english to german is that through the reverse translation model
exactly yeah okay cool uh and you're saying back translation
helps uh generate higher quality translations
uh because of regularization is that it ah it's not just
regularization it also the really useful thing is it gives you lots
of clean output data so let's say you ought to be a good
german to english translation model you kind of need both to understand
german we'll also be able to write lots of
fluent english as well and then the english grammar too and the back
translation gives you a way of incorporating tons of
additional language data beyond what you have translations for
um okay so kind of combines translation [inaudible] language
model and you can also um iterate this procedure too so you can
uh use it use that whole [inaudible] we described before to train a better model
and then uh
do this to help you generate better translate better back translations which
you can use to train again and this can be really helpful i mean it
helps even in english german but it's particularly helpful in cases
where you don't have much data so this is on a [inaudible] to english translation
where there isn't a lot of parallel data but you can
uh get really large improvements by just iterating back translation uh this
was recent work from FAIR which i forgot to reference for
um and again here are some results on uh uh i think this is english german
showing some good improvements uh one of the direction um in machine
translation people are exploring now is a
massively multilingual mt so people are trying to
not just translate between two languages but trying to
take dozens of 100 languages and try and train a single neural network that could
translate between all of these um and if you do this you start see um
a big improvement particularly in languages where you don't have much text
presumably the model's learning some kind of
more general language independent information
okay so the last topic i want to cover in this is a really important one which
is that self-supervised learning um all right so um young is just seeing
this cake now but i think it's actually a good image for this so the idea is
um really that to learn stuff like most of the information
we need is going to be most learning we do has to be unsupervised so
we have huge amounts of text without any labels on it
and we just have a little bit of um sort of supervised training data that's
represented by the cake here being the unsupervised learning and the
supervised learning just being a little bit of icing on top of the cake
i think actually um the recent self-supervised learning from nlp has
really proved this metaphor to work okay so
um i'm going to describe quite a few methods for how you do self-supervised
learning for nlp um just so you can try and get some ideas
as to what's actually working uh so
uh the first one to describe is word2vec so the area word2vec was trying to
i think it's really the first paper that showed
uh got people excited about self-supervised learning in NLP
uh but have his previous work from uh [inaudible] which had
also shown some good gains um so the goal here is going to be trying
to learn what's called word embedding so vector space representations for words
and the hope is by that by looking at unlabeled english
text we can learn something about what these words mean
that's what the intuition behind all this is that if two words are
ok close together in the text then they're likely to have some kind of
relationship between each other um so the pre-training task we're going
to do is going to be a filling in the blanks task
so um in this sentence i'm going to mask out this word in the middle which
is unicorns and try and predict what this word should be
based on the surrounding context and hope would be that
words like unknown silver-haired and horned will somehow
are more likely to occur in the context of a unicorn than they are
i know a word like some other animal
um so basically this is gonna be a very simple model where basically we're gonna
take all these context words we're gonna apply some linear projection
to these and map all that to a fixed size context
and then just do a softmax over our vocabulary
uh so it looks a little bit like a convolutional language model the only
difference is we're predicting the word in the middle not the word at the end um
and in practice this model was um just a shallow linear projection and didn't
was not a very deep model okay um so
one of the things we find interesting about this was these um word weddings
to show some kind of surprising stretches to them uh
i'll show you how it was fun this is like
people debated about how meaningful is this um
but basically the claim was that if you took you're embedding of the word
king which you train like this and you subtract you're ready for word man then
you add the embedding of the word woman you'll get something that's fairly close
to the embedding for the word queen so somehow um
it's just this kind of unsupervised fill in the blanks learning task
isn't using this kind of linear structure with kind of meaningful
differences between vectors okay so i mean this
was great and the really good thing about this was that it's a really really
fast thing to do so you could train this on
billions of words texts you back in 2013.
um but there's a big limitation which is these word
embeddings are independent of the context so
um you get like one vector per word in your vocabulary
um but it doesn't know anything about how that word relational works
and we know that to in language like um a sentence is involved in just by
words it depends each word interacts with other words
somehow and these interactions are in some way
it's a really powerful thing so in one example
obvious example is like ambiguous words so lots of words can have many different
meanings and these word vectors won't capture
that or the best [inaudible] of all
the meanings so how do we add context to these well
um see the most obvious way is to
do a language model i think i'm missing a slide here uh basically
what we do is train a conditional language model sorry an unconditional
language model this is going to be exactly the kind of model i described
earlier in the talk and then um
given this language model the language model will be outputting hidden states every
time step predicting the next word and instead when we want to self-supervised
learning what we're going to do is replace these outputs with um
some other output that depends on our task so the pre-training phase is just
going to be predict the next word but then kind of the icing on the cake
or supervised learning will be the predicts some other property so i'll
show you an example here for a task called
speech tagging which is trying to say put some labels in every word here
so turn light label scientists as noun and distinctive as
an adjective um but you can actually fit all kinds of
tasks into this kind of framework um so for example maybe you can fit
something like this is a sentiment analysis task where
you're given some text to predict like from an amazon review and predict
the uh rating so
um this is a review that says what can i say about its banana slicer that hasn't
already been said about the wheel penicillin or the iphone and this review
got five stars so here was you're going to predict one
output from this language model which is going to be the
uh a token at the end which you can some kind of test specific
label so one of the really nice things about
this approach called gpt was that it kind of eliminated tasks
specific modeling so now suddenly we have
one model which you can pre-train and we can that fine tune that model to do
basically any task we want to do like
classification um so before this
um there's actually a few years when people were building all these crazy
architectures that you build different architectures to do build a
question answering model let's do a sentiment analysis model or
something um now you train pre-train one big model and then it's
really easy to find units do whatever you like
so that was a really big step forward um unfortunately model has kind of the
obvious limitation i said the important thing to do was kind of contextualize
words so like let words know build word representations depend on the
context but if you pre-train this language model
you can only really condition on your left word context
so your expectations for each word necessarily can't depend on the
representation for any future words
um and that kind of limits what the model
can do quite a lot um there's one kind of obvious fix to
that which is um the approach taken by elmo
um so elmo run the training one left to right language model
um also train the second language model which operates
in the reverse direction so this is like um
so it's the last word in document and it keeps trying to create the previous ones
and then you get word representations by concatenating the output layers of your
left right model and your right left model
uh so this model is in some ways better in that like now your word
representations can't condition on local context and are
right with context and that's really helpful for lots of
tasks but it's still kind of limited and that
you don't really much like interactions in these contexts so these
um you get this shallow kind of concatenation of left
representation the right representation and what you really do is having like
rich interactions between the left context and the right context
right um and all this brings me to BERT which is
uh maybe you've heard of which has made a very big difference in lp
um so bert actually looks quite a lot like word2vec
it is basically a fill in the blanks task so you take some text
you hide some tokens by masking them out and then you just try and fill it in the
mask so here's text like something is a golden
something muppets and you fill in there yeah
the thing i want you to notice is firstly it actually looks quite a lot
like word2vec um word2vec was also given some text
fill in the blanks um the reasons works much better is that
in word2vec you would just had this linear projection like
including the context words whereas you have them
a very large transformer uh which look in much more context and well much
more interactions in that context so there is a question here how are
contextual representations maintained when fine-tuning for a specific task
um how are they maintained um i guess um it's not clear they are
maintained um so when you find your particular task
you kind of let the model to learn enough general stuff that language
the pre-trained task and then doing the fine tuning probably i guess it's
forgetting a lot of stuff but it doesn't need to solve this
particular task so if you're fine-tuning on a sentiment analysis
or something it could probably probably kind of lose a lot of this
information during fine tuning that seems fine thanks
okay um so BERT it worked very well um they gave
like quite large improvements on a bunch of tasks
um it was actually achieving the performance of humans or at least
humans approximated by Amazon Mechanical Turk
on a bunch of important uh question answering benchmarks
but um BERT was definitely not the end of the story here um
but i've lots of people very excited about self supervised training
um so just to quickly summarize details there so
it's very simple model is just going to mask out 15 of the tokens
and try and fill in the masks um to build on that um doesn't work at
Facebook Yinhan Liu which looked at scaling up bert um
so can you tell the combination actually actually has second pre-training
objective which we showed didn't actually help
so can i read can i ask a question for the slide
so there there were three bars i think i missed one point
the the dark blue what is the dark blue so we have amazon turk there
thank you sorry i said that um dark blue hair is previously that so
okay which was um these models were probably elmo which is
oh yeah okay so previously i was definitely using
self-supervised training but uh but improved relevant by having
this kind of like i see and GLUE actually it's a benchmark
that we've been uh creating here at nyu exactly some students were involved
yeah so yeah glue is a big benchmark it's very
important okay um so to beat BERT it turned out all
you had to do was firstly simplify training objective then just
scale it up so scaling up here means bigger batch sizes
uh huge numbers of gpus more free training text and
then um you get very large gains on top of
work so yellow here is then this new roberta model
and uh actually roberta the question answering is like
superhuman by quite a few points and also on this GLUE benchmark from nyu is
also uh outperformed people
and this isn't really about doing anything smart it's just
taking self supervised training and doing it more
alright um how why why do you say like if you go on this slide here so there is
a very large improvement between uh bert and then roberta in the GLUE
but not such a huge uh change maybe in the squad or is
it just a zooming factor i'm like um
maybe it's just a zooming factor right those bars on the left are taller maybe
yeah i think maybe the scales distorting i think the
point is if compared to human performance um
i know um bert was 0.6 points best of the people whereas
roberta is uh three and a half points better
so by that metric is actually quite a big jump
okay uh so let's quickly discuss a few of the other
things people have been doing in self-supervised training and
so there's one called XLNet now um basically so input when you predict all
the mask tokens you predict all the masks conditionally
independently um XLNet has a trick lets you
predict these mass tokens auto regressively but in random order
and they claim some improvements from doing that
it's also uh SpanBERT which uh rather than masking out words you're gonna mask
out a sequence of consecutive words um there
is ELECTRA which um rather than
masking words we're going to substitute words with
sort of similar ones and then have a binary classification problem to tell
you which word's changed or not uh
it's albert which is um bert but you tie the weights across layers um also
um XLM and XLMR which looking to do this multilingually it turns out
basically you run the BERT pre-training objective but rather's
feeding in english text you feed in text in every language you can
find it does a great job learning cross-lingual structure
um the key point what you take from this is
really like these are all kind of variation
um there's but in the end like lots of different
things work and the important thing is you have
big models you have bi-directional interactions between the words
and you uh if anything the scale you do this
is the most important thing um so
one limitation these models i described is they're only doing kind of text
classification problems but often we'll want to do
problems where the output isn't the classification problem is actually
output some more text uh pre-training for sequence sequence
modeling uh two papers came out about the same
time for this one which i was involved in um
called BART and T5 um so these models basically are going to
pre-train sequence sequence models by denoising text
um the tree training objective looks kind of like that basically all you're
going to do is take some text corrupt it somehow by
applying some kind of masking scheme and then
rather than predict fill in the blanks you're going
to feed the corrupted text into a seq2seq model and try and predict
the complete outputs and um
and this is kind of nice because then you can actually go beyond just masking
text you can apply like any random uh corruption thing that you want
so for example you can shuffle sentences or delete whole
phrases or it's a new phrases and the seq2seq framework
is very flexible um but it turns out just doing simple
masking actually works about as well as anything else
um and then if you do this and as well as like it
doing well things benchmarks like squad and GLUE which are classification benchmarks
you can also get [inaudible] results on um
tasks like summarization so um where the output is a text so
on the left here we've got some lengthy document fed in we ask them all
to produce some kind of summary of this and uh it is a great job like actually
uses context from across the whole document and solves things like
co-reference and generally as far as you can tell seems
to show some understanding of the inputs um okay we're running out of time
um so briefly um i don't think it's the end story like
the nlp is now solved um a few open questions which i think
are interesting including how do we integrate like
background knowledge into this do we just want
these models to try and memorize the whole internet or should we
build memory mechanisms somehow uh as someone brought up earlier how do
we model long documents we're typically doing 512 tokens here
how can we do say a whole book at once
um one unsatisfying thing about this is like we have like the same model
architecture can solve all kinds of problems but it tends to not be able to
solve all these problems at once and typically
you fine-tune a separate model for each task
it would be great if you actually have like one model solves everything
um and um it's kind of related to that like we
basically get human level performance the main task where you have say a hundred
thousand uh labeled examples you're learning from
but can we build models will do well with
like 1000 or 10 or 1 labeled examples
and finally that people bring these questions that's where these models are
just actually understanding language i was
really good at breaking benchmarks okay so to wrap up this
uh lecture um i think the main takeaways from this uh um
these kind of low bias models like transformers work great we shouldn't try
to explicitly model linguistic structure we
should have very expressive models and show them lots
of text and let them learn whatever structure they need um
predicting words and texts is a great uh unsupervised learning objective um
but if you want to understand what's crucial to like incorporate words in
context in particular bi-directional context
okay so that's all i have to thank you very much for listening
let's see if we have some questions now i think there will be
several thank you mike yeah there's a whole bunch of
discussions while we while you're talking okay links to various papers
and explanations of various concepts in the background
okay um any more questions uh yeah i had one um on one of the open questions
it's like understanding whether or not these
models are actually uh understanding the language
what are some ways that exist right now to quantify and measure that
um and how like how how would we do that yeah okay so
what typically happens is someone says i know
these models aren't understanding language if they could they'd be able to solve this
new task that they're introducing then they
introduce some new tasks which they can't do and then
say bert isn't doing it then next week
someone trains a bigger model and then actually gets human performance
on this task and i think really
what's happening is like some people just have intuitions that
this kind of these neural networks can't be understanding language
and they must just be gaming data sets somehow
and the extent that these models do well there must be kind of weird biases in
our data sets and make the moles can exploit without really
understanding anything um and it's definitely true that like a
lot of data sets do have biases in them and like it's
kind of hard to make ones that don't do it takes a lot of skill but
on the other hand it's like people are failing to produce good counter examples
so what these models can't do like basically
sorry it's a good example in recent times was the
winograd schema results where you know winograd schemas are those
sentences that are ambiguous and there is a reference there is a
pronoun that refers to one of the words and you can tell
which word the pronoun refers to unless you know something about how the word
works right so the standard example is uh the trophy
doesn't fit in the suitcase because it's too large
or the trophy doesn't fit in the suitcase because it's too small
and you know in in one case the the trophy
refers to the the the pronoun refers to the trophy in the other case it refers
to the the suitcase and there was a list of
those and people created a data set of those things and
until about two years ago the best results were around 60
for computers humans do 95 or something but um the best uh uh
the best you know artificial systems were getting about 60
and now i think it's about 90 percent yeah
right yeah something like that right you don't even get any training dates for
these this is just a purely unsupervised
problem right and so so the question is you know it's clear
that those systems have learned something about
uh the role of objects and you know a little bit about how the world works
by just observing statistics about text but it's relatively superficial it's not
um i mean you know as it's pretty obvious
when you look at text that's generated uh you know we're talking about unicorn
and then the first sentence is uh unicorns has four horns right which of
course doesn't make sense because unicorns have only one
that's kind of the point of being a unicorn so um
so the whole idea of i mean the whole con problem of learning common sense
uh has not been solved very far from it but those systems but they work
surprisingly well i mean it's surprisingly it's surprising how far you
can go with just you know looking at text
uhum yeah learaning common sense is super
hard because in some sense the things you want to learn
are things that aren't written down like no one ever writes down
common sense knowledge yeah probably no one ever writes down like a unicorn has
exactly one corn and not for i mean it's just because everyone knows that um
so probably there are limitations to what you can learn from just
looking at text but can you can you tell us something about the
the word i mean about some of the work you're doing on sort of grounded
language uh sure yeah so i mean um
i put nothing back grounding in this um but there's a whole
interesting topic and so i think it's really interesting trying
[inaudible] people don't use text because
it's like it's a representation of the world um
so one type of guy's really interested in like trying to like kind of
ground dialogue usage and goals so um run some people like chit chat systems
that talk to each other or talk to people to have a conversation
like can you build systems where you try to achieve some goal um we
had some work a couple years ago and doing a
this in the context of negotiations so trying to
um there's two of you which are trying to have a conversation just kind
of crank on some agreement with each other
um and the only way you can come to agreement is by
having a dialogue in natural language and there's like some outcomes which are
good for use and what's good for them you have to find some compromise
um and then yeah i'm kind of interested in the setting
because um yeah it seems like
you actually using language for a purpose is gonna be really crucial to a really
understanding things like i think
that's going to get hints like there's limits to what we'll learn from just
like purely observational use of language and so just purely
seeing text out there in the world that other people wrote like really
to understand things you want to be agents which
are using language to try and choose some goal and interact with people and
seeing what works and learning from that kind of signal as
well um maybe that's it's just the cherry on the
icing on the cake or whatever but i think that's
it is that you need a cherry more questions from the audience come on
guys don't be too shy uh i have a question uh
the first point on the open questions how should we
integrate world knowledge so uh the way i i was thinking about is that
these billion parameter transformers have
so much information about the world in them and then if we
try to fine-tune or train this model on some new data could we like forget
some of the earlier concepts that uh this model had learnt and how would
we like quantify what concepts like
has the model forgotten apart from the validation set
does that make sense um yeah so probably you will forget i mean
probably if you fine-tune this model to do
something that doesn't need well knowledgeable happily forget
all the knowledge you told it um i mean there's some evidence these models
are like memorizing quite a lot of facts so there's a remarkable
uh result recently from this paper this google system called T5 which i think is
12 billion parameters and it's just trained in a
self-supervised way and if you have people
and then you um just fine tune to answer questions
which could be questions about anything but you don't show it any
you don't show up wikipedia or something to let you know you just like see what's
memorized and you can test how much knowledge is in
the model from that and um it's not safety after that but it
like it's kind of scarily good it's like
it turns out if you have 12 billion parameters you train for a long time you
can just fit huge numbers of facts into these
levels i'm not sure it's like the most
desirable way necessarily to memorize knowledge but
um seems somewhat effective
okay that was it thank you everyone for attending
thank you so much mike for uh for giving a guest lecture
um it's good to hear that stuff from the horse's mouth
and we'll see see everyone again next uh next week
we're gonna we'll actually tomorrow right tomorrow we're gonna be
implementing everything from scratch don't forget so tomorrow you get the
gory details from the code side of all of this
and then uh monday you'll hear from you'll hear about
graph neural nets from Xavier Bresson actually about graph neural net and
graph knowledge is that is graph knowledge used for language as
well somehow because right i i don't know i have not really
uh knowledgeable about this part of the
field well so you can view to some extent you can view
all the those supervised training in text
uh like word2vec uh bert et cetera they use a graph and the graph is
how uh you know how often two words appear next to each other
or some distance away from each other in the text
that's you know the graph of similarity between words basically is determined by
how far you know how often they're they appear nearby
yeah that's that's when you decide to put them in the input of a neural net
because they appear you know within the sequence so you can think of
those those those are supervised learning systems as
basically a very simple form of graph neural net
well the graph always has the same structure it's always linear but and it
always uh indicates your your neighbors in a
text all right thank you so much everyone
have a good evening bye-bye